Mary Ellen Chase Literary Manuscripts, 1937-1968
Mortimer Rare Book Room, William Allan Neilson Library, Smith College
Mary Ellen Chase Literary Manuscripts
1937-1968
Chase, Mary Ellen, 1887-1973
33
7 boxes (3 linear ft.)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
The bulk of the collection consists of manuscripts of novels, children's books, memoirs, biblical studies, articles, and book reviews.
(The biographical note was written by Elizabeth Kates in 1999 for the Smith College Archives collection of Professor Chase's papers located in that collection.)
Mary Ellen Chase was born on February 24, 1887 in Blue Hill, Maine. Her parents were deeply religious Protestants and Mary Ellen was one of eight children who received a thorough biblical education as well as an academic one. She began writing at the age of sixteen and by her death on July 28, 1973, had published more than thirty essays, novels, and biographies.
At the age of nineteen, Chase took a leave from the University of Maine, where she was enrolled as an undergraduate, in order to teach in a one-room school in Buck's Harbor, Maine. Following her graduation, she taught for three years in Wisconsin at a coeducational boarding school and later for two years at a private girl's school in Chicago, Illinois. At that point in time, Chase fell ill and was advised by her doctor that a move to Montana would improve her health. During her time there, Chase taught public school and wrote two novels.
Upon full recovery, Chase took a teaching position at the University of Minnesota where she also studied and earned her MA in 1918 and later her Ph.D. in 1922. In 1926 she was hired by Smith College where she taught courses on the English novel and the King James Version of the Bible. During her time at Smith, Chase became a respected colleague, teacher, and friend to many. Her courses, taken by English majors and non-English majors alike, were some of the most popular on campus. In addition, Chase's home on Paradise Road became a favorite place for her students to go for good conversation and cookies. Despite her success as an author, teaching remained her true love throughout her career. She viewed teaching as the main source of meaning in her life. An extremely dedicated professor, Chase believed that "the personality of the teacher is more important than her intellectual attainments" and that "if the teacher has no enthusiasm for teaching and for subject matter, her students will learn little." She was very excited about her field of expertise and hoped to similarly inspire her students.
Mary Ellen Chase has come to be known as one of the great American novelists. Much of her work was inspired by her childhood in Maine and several of her novels are autobiographical. The Goodly Heritage (1932) and A Goodly Fellowship (1939) are about her childhood and how she became a teacher, respectively. Chase also wrote several books for children and more than one of her novels became best-sellers. Chase's popularity and skill at public speaking earned her many invitations to lecture around the country. She was awarded honorary degrees at the University of Maine, Bowdoin, and Colby Colleges, Smith College, and Northeastern University. Her work was also acknowledged by the Women's National Book Association in 1956 when she was awarded the Constance Lindsay Skinner Award.
After her retirement in 1955 at the age of sixty-eight, Chase continued to live on-campus with her long-time companion, Eleanor Duckett, and her dog, Gregory. She spent summers in Maine at her home, "Windswept," and journeyed to England where she took Hebrew classes at Cambridge in order to better understand the Old Testament. She also taught two adult education seminars on the Bible at Radcliffe College. In 1968, Smith College acknowledged her dedication to the students and the College with a new dormitory, the Mary Ellen Chase House.
The Mary Ellen Chase Literary Manuscripts consist of 3 linear feet of material, dating from 1937 to 1968. The bulk of the collection consists of manuscripts of her novels, memoirs, biblical studies, articles, and book reviews, as well as a few miscellaneous personal items. The majority of the collection came to the Rare Book Room directly from Chase over a period of time, including items that were part of her estate. The manuscript of Dawn in Lyonnesse was given to the collection by Raymond P. Putman in memory of Natalie Starr Putman (Smith College Class of 1933). There are additional items that were donated by Eleanor Duckett and Esther C. Dunn. The letters of Mary Ellen Chase to Grace Cooper were given to the Library by Ann Gilbert McDonald.
The majority of Chase's literary manuscripts are located in other repositories. See the section entitled "Related Material" for assistance in finding other literary manuscripts. The Smith College Archives has files related to Chase's teaching career in the English Department of Smith College.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. PERSONAL PAPERS (1947-1968)
II. BOOKS (1937-1968)
III. ARTICLES AND OTHER WRITINGS (1933-1966)
IV. BOOK REVIEWS BY MARY ELLEN CHASE (1954-1966)
V. OVERSIZE
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The manuscripts are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Mortimer Rare Book Room without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The majority of the collection came to the Rare Book Room directly from Chase over a period of time, including items that were part of her estate. The manuscript of Dawn in Lyonnesse was given to the collection by Raymond P. Putman in memory of Natalie Starr Putman (Smith College Class of 1933). There are additional items that were donated by Eleanor Duckett and Esther C. Dunn. The letters of Mary Ellen Chase to Grace Cooper were given to the Library by Ann Gilbert McDonald.
Search Terms
Chase, Mary Ellen, 1887-1973; Cooper, Grace; Smith College--Faculty; American literature--History and Criticism-Sources; Bible as literature; Bible--Introductions; Gogorzo, Maitland de
Additional Information
Related Material
Researchers should also view:
In Georgetown University Libraries. Special Collections. The Joseph G. E. Hopkins Papers contains letters from MEC.
In Indiana University. Lilly Library. Sylvia Plath Manuscripts, 1932-1977 contains letters from MEC.
In The Massachusetts Historical Society. Ellery Sedgwick Papers, 1898-1969 contains letters from MEC.
In Rockefeller Archive Center. Rockefeller Family Archives. Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Papers, 1858-1957 contains correspondence between John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and MEC in regards to Chase's biography of Abby.
In Smith College Archives. RG 42 Mary Ellen Chase Papers, 1893-1995.
In Smith College Libraries. Mortimer Rare Book Room. MS 25 Hampshire Bookshop records, 1916-1971. (Contains letters from Mary Ellen Chase to Marion Dodd and others, as well as autograph manuscripts and typescripts.)
In the University of Minnesota Libraries. Manuscripts Division. Mary Ellen Chase Manuscript 01. Contains a partial manuscript of The Prophets for the Common Reader, plus two letters.
In the University of New England Libraries, Maine Women Writers Collection
In the Folger Library, University of Maine, Orono, Maine
- SERIES I. PERSONAL PAPERS 1947-1968
  This series contains a few personal items of Chase, a few letters written and/or received by her, the notebooks she kept during her study of Hebrew at Cambridge University and other miscellaneous items.
- SERIES II. BOOKS1937-1968
  This series includes the manuscripts of a few of Chase's literary output, namely her novels and children's books, memoir and biblical studies.
- SERIES III. ARTICLES AND OTHER WRITINGS (1933-1966)
  Chase wrote extensively for popular magazines. Included in this series are the manuscripts of a few of the articles she wrote for this media. In addition, there are some speeches and other materials whose purpose is not clearly identified.
- SERIES IV. BOOK REVIEW BY MARY ELLEN CHASE 1954-1966
  This series includes reviews by Mary Ellen Chase, arranged alphabetically by the author.
- SERIES I. PERSONAL PAPERS 1947-1968
  - Appreciation certificate, College of St. Catherine, St. Paul, Minnesota, 1968 Jun 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of Mary Ellen Chase (to and from), 1906-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2a-n)
  - Letter. ALS to Grace Cooper, Orono, Maine. Ms. Chase describes in detail her room, her students and school-teaching and the landscape in South Brookville, Maine. [8 pages and envelope], 1906 Apr 20, postmark (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Letter. ALS to Grace Cooper, Orono, Maine. Ms. Chase describes the sea, her arrival at South Brooksville in the rain, a "foolish" girl who wandered into her schoolhouse, her boarding house and her teaching ("rain or shine--well or ill.") [4 pages and envelope], 1906 May 10, postmark (Box 1, Folder 2b)
  - Letter. ALS to Grace Cooper, Orono, Maine. Ms. Chase discusses the end of school, her vacation plans and the difficulties she had driving the family cow home. [7 pages and envelope], 1906 Jul 4 (Box 1, Folder 2c)
  - Letter. ALS to Grace Cooper, Orono, Maine. Ms. Chase describes the sea and her feelings at a clam bake. She also writes about New England "country" people and about the writers who try to portray them. [19 pages and envelope], 1906 Sep 3, postmark (Box 1, Folder 2d)
  - Letter. ALS to Grace Cooper, Lansing, Michigan. Ms. Chase discusses winter in Maine, snowshoeing, her family's cook, books she likes and a date she had with Ellis. She has just turned 20 years old. [8 pages and envelope], 1907 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 2e)
  - Letter. ALS to Grace Cooper, Lansing, Michigan. Ms. Chase describes the signs of spring, her backache and her boarding house. She notes that she will be going back to college next year and complains about her poor eyes. [13 leaves and envelope], 1907 Apr 29, postmark (Box 1, Folder 2f)
  - Letter. ALS to Grace Cooper, Lansing, Michigan. Ms. Chase discusses her life back at College and how she dislikes Orono in comparison to Blue Hill. She mentions various mutual friends. [17 pages and envelope], 1907 Sep 22, postmark (Box 1, Folder 2g)
  - Letter. ALS to Grace Cooper, Lansing, Michigan. Ms. Chase sends get well wishes. [7 pages and envelope], 1908 Oct 15, postmark (Box 1, Folder 2h)
  - Letter. ALS to Grace Cooper, Lansing, Michigan. Ms. Chase sends get well wishes and describes the weather and the woods. She says it is hard to study and asks Grace to come back to Orono for a year. [10 pages and envelope], 1909 Aug 8, postmark (Box 1, Folder 2i)
  - Letter. TLS from Rebecca West to MEC giving Ms. Chase permission to reprint her "Travelling in America." Also mentions Mina Curtiss. [1 leaf], 1929 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 2j)
  - Letter. TLS to [Martha A.] Kirsten thanking her for her letter on Chase's "A Goodly Fellowship." [1 leaf], 1940 Feb 24 (Box 1, Folder 2k)
  - Letter. TLS from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to MEC in the Cooley Dickinson Hospital, Northampton, Mass. conveying wishes for her recovery. He encloses remarks of Mr. King on Ms. Chase's work (no longer with the letter). [2 leaves], 1950 Jul 31 (Box 1, Folder 2l)
  - Letter. AMS from Cecilia V. Sargent. Sargent writes of her retirement in Camden, Maine, and her attempting to write a novel at 76 years of age. Now at 78 the novel is published. She thanks Chase for inspiring her in this pursuit. [3 leaves], 1971 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 2m)
  - Correspondence received by MEC. The letter from Newton (The Thacher School, Ojai, Calif.), may be from her nephew., 1968 Mar-Aug (Box 1, Folder 2n)
  - Course outline, Victorian Literature, Honors Unit. 1 notebook, AMsS, 1950s. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Also contains outline for Seminar in Writing, [Smith College] 428.
  - Hebrew study notebooks, Cambridge, England. 4 notebooks, AMsS, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Photograph of MEC, by Eric Stahlberg, Northampton, Mass., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of MEC. MEC with 3 siblings, she is identified as "Minnie." Taken by Harry Smith, Bucksport, Me. and photograph dated 1917 taken by Sam M. Judd, Reid Corner, Minneapolis, inscribed by Chase: "To my friend Mrs. Peters with my love-July 28, '17, Mary Ellen Chase.", undated, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6a)
  - Royalty statements, Macmillan, 1968 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Stationery of MEC - blank pages, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- SERIES II. BOOKS1937-1968
  - Dawn in Lyonesse (New York: Macmillan, 1938)
    - Original draft, AMsS, 1 notebook. Contains an inscription by MEC dated 24 Dec 1948: "For Natalie Starr Putman to whom this book was dedicated in 1937.", 1937 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dolly Moses: the Cat and the Clam Chowder (New York: W. W. Norton, 1964)
    - [First draft], AMs, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Second draft ("2nd try"), AMs, 1963 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - [Third draft], AMsS, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Donald McKay and the Clipper Ships (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1959)
    - Notebook I. AMs Began, 1958 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Notebook II. AMs, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Typescripts, carbon, corrected. TMs. 99 leaves, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Edge of Darkness (New York: W. W. Norton, 1957), (Original and revised manuscripts are in the Smith College Archives.)
    - Typescripts, corrected, with printer's annotations. TMs. 289 leaves, 1957 Jun 2 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
    - Galley proofs - See Oversize
  - The Girl from the Big Horn Country (New York: A. L. Burt, 1916)
    - Dust jacket, undated (Box 2, Folder 18a)
  - A Goodly Fellowship (New York: Macmillan, 1939)
    - AMs. 4 notebooks, 1939, Laid in: "This manuscript is gladly given to the cause of the War Bond Rally held in Northampton, on January 25, 1944 in John M. Greene Hall. The book was begun on April 16th, 1939 and written largely at Juniper Lodge, Chocorug, N.H. during the summer of 1939. It was finished on Sep. 17th, 1939...." AmsS. See in Oversize: Drawing of Blue Hill Harbor, Maine, illustration for A Goodly Heritage, by Maitland de Gogorzo. (Box 2, Folder 19-22)
  - A Journey to Boston, a Novel (New York: W. W. Norton, c 1965)
    - Typescripts, carbons, mimeographs, with printer's annotations. TMs. 84 leaves, 1965 Jan 6 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Life and Language in the Old Testament (New York: W. W. Norton, 1955)
    - Typescript, corrected, with printer's annotations. 240 leaves, 1955 Jul 19 (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
  - The Prophets for the Common Reader (New York: W. W. Norton, 1963), (Earlier manuscripts for this title are in the Smith College Archives.)
    - Typescript, corrected, with printer's annotations. 180 leaves, 1963 Apr 3 (Box 3, Folder 27-29)
  - The Psalms for the Common Reader (New York: W. W. Norton, 1962)
    - Typescript, corrected, with printer's annotations. 213 leaves, 1961 Dec 13 (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
    - Galley proofs - See Oversize
  - Richard Mansfield: the Prince of Donkeys (New York: W. W. Norton, 1964
    - Draft 1, AMs. l notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Draft 2, AMs. 19 leaves, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - TMs. 22 leaves, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - TMs, carbon. 22 leaves, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Sailing the Seven Seas (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1958)
    - TMs, carbon. 95 leaves, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Victoria: A Pig in a Pram (New York: W. W. Norton, c 1963)
    - TMs, carbon. 19 leaves, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - A Walk on an Iceberg (New York: W. W. Norton, 1966)
    - Original draft. AMsS 1 notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - [Revised draft] AMsS. 28 leaves, 1966? (Box 3, Folder 40)
      On tp: "Originally written at Rockport: May 23rd-May 30th [1966?]"
    - Typescript, carbon. 29 leaves. Leaf 29 is an original typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - The White Gate: Adventures in the Imagination of a Child (New York: W. W. Norton, 1954)
    - Typescript, carbons, mimeographs, with printer's annotations. TMs. 144 leaves, 1954 May 13 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - TMs, Chapter 7. On chapter tp: "Suppressed copy." Laid in: Chapter VII being rewritten." Leaves [68]-73., undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Revision notes. AMs. 2 leaves, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Windswept (New York: Macmillan, 1941)
    - (Drawings, photographs and letters related to the novel are in the Smith College Archives.)
    - Original draft, AMs. 10 notebooks, 1940-[1941] (Box 4, Folder 45-54)
      On tp: of the 1st notebook: "Actual writing of this novel began on 12th November 1940 at 16 Paradise Pond …" Laid in: "The original manuscript began November 12, 1941 in Northampton. Finished September 2, 1942 at Windswept, Petit Manan Point, Maine." Dates incorrect on MEC's note in that her novel was published in 1941.
    - Revised draft, AMs. 16 notebooks, [1941] (Box 5, Folder 55-70)
      Laid in: "Dear Margaret Erierson: I am very happy to give to the Smith College Library the manuscript of Windswept in its original and its revised form.... because the College has given me the fifteen happiest years of my life. It may interest you to know that much of the novel was written in Library 35 and 36." AMsS, dtd 1942 Feb
- SERIES III. ARTICLES AND OTHER WRITINGS (1933-1966)
  - "An Ancient Democracy to a Modern," Common Ground 3:2 (1943):65-71
    - An Ancient Democracy to a Modern: an address … January 11, 1942 given at the … New York Society for Ethical Culture. TMs, mimeograph with corrections. 7 leaves, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - An Ancient Democracy to a Modern: an address given before the Secondary Education Association on Feb. 28th, 1942 in Philadelphia. TMsS, with corrections. 20 leaves, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Ancient Greek Ideals. AMsS, [12] leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - "Are You Afraid of Snakes?" Reader's Digest 69 (Jul 1956):45-48
    - Are You Afraid of Snakes? AMsS, 11 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - "Confidences of a Lecturer," Commonweal 18 (May 26, 1933):100-102
    - AMs, 23 leaves, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - "Five Literary Portraits," The Massachusetts Review 3 (Spring 1962): 511-516
    - AMs, 1 notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 76)
      Manuscript has title: Literary Portraits: Willa Cather, Sarah Orne Jewett, Gertrude Stein, Rose Macaulay, Dorothy Sayers
    - TMsS. carbon, 8 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 77)
      Manuscript has title: Some Brief Literary Portraits.
  - For Victoria Louise Schrager. TMsS, mimeo, 4 leaves, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    "Given at the Memorial Assembly at Smith College, Wednesday, Oct. 27, 1943 at 8:30 A.M."
  - Maine. TMs, with corrections. 15 leaves, incomplete ms., undated (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - "Memorial Day, 1900," Ladies Home Journal 74 (May 1957):56+.
    - AMsS, 20 pages, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - "Pitfalls of a Perfectionist," Coronet 40 (Sep 1956): 46-48
      - AMsS, 12 leaves, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 81)
        Draft has title: Pitfalls of Perfection: the Myth of 100%
    - The Psalms of Maine. TMsS, mimeo, 3 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - "She Misses Some Goals," Life 41 (Dec. 24, 1956):23-25
      - First draft, AMs, 8 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 83)
        Has title: The American Woman: A Diagnosis of Her Present State
      - Second draft, AMsS, 10 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 84)
        Has title: The American Woman.
      - TMs, 8 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 85)
      - Mimeo copy with corrections. [14] leaves, 1956 Oct 25 (Box 6, Folder 86)
      - Letter. TLS from Ralph Graves, Life. In regard to the ms. of 1962 Oct 25. [1] leaf, 1956 Oct 26 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Smith College: A Definition. Printed broadside. 3 copies, undated (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - "Thank-You Is a Lovely Word"
      - [Draft 1?], AMs, written in pencil [8] leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 89)
      - [Draft 2?], AMsS, written in ink [10] leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 90)
      - TLS from Harlin Quist, Collier Books (1 leaf) and signed contract (5 leaves) in regard to "Thank-You Is a Lovely Word", 1962 Oct 12 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Values in Literature [by] Mary Ellen Chase, Arno Jewett, William Evans. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, c 1968.
      - [Draft 1], AMsS, 5 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 92)
        Has title: Introduction
      - [Draft 2], AMsS, 7 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 93)
      - TMsS, carbon, 7 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 94)
      - AMsS, 9 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 95)
        Has title: Introductions to Units + mimeo list of "Table of Contents," 6 leaves, dtd 25 Jun 1963
      - TMsS, carbon, 8 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 96)
        Has title: Introductions to Units
    - What Do You Expect of College for Your Daughter? AMs, [8] pages, undated (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - "Why Teach Literature?" Literature Today, no. 5 (New York: Houghton Mifflin, c1966), 1966 (Box 6)
      - [Draft 1], AMs, [13] leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 98)
      - [Draft 2], AMsS, [15] leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 99)
      - TMsS, carbon, 16 leaves, undated (Box 6, Folder 100)
      - TLS from William A. Jamison, Houghton Mifflin in regard to the publication of "Why Teach Literature?" in Literature Today. [1] leaf, 1967 Jun 26 (Box 6, Folder 101)
      - Published work. 3 copies, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 102)
      - Miscellaneous sheets., undated (Box 6, Folder 102a)
- SERIES IV. BOOK REVIEW BY MARY ELLEN CHASE 1954-1966
  - Gildersleeve, Virginia C. A Hoard for Winter (New York: Columbia University Press, 1962), AMsS. [3] leaves, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Haller, William. The Elect Nation: the Meaning and Relevance of Foxe's Book of Martyrs (New York: Harper & Row, 1963), AMs. [3] leaves, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Jewett, Sarah Orne. A White Heron: A Story of Maine; edited and illustrated by Barbara Cooney (New York: Thomas Y Crowell, 1963), AMsS. [2] leaves, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - O'Connor, Frank. The Mirror in the Roadway: A Study of the Modern Novel (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1956), AMsS. [3] leaves, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Read, Miss. Village School (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1955), AMsS. [2] leaves, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Starkey, Marion L. The Congregational Way (New York: Doubleday, 1966), TMs. 4 leaves, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Worcester, Gurdon S. The Singing Flute (New York: I. Obolensky, 1963), AMsS. [2] leaves, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 109)
- SERIES V. OVERSIZE
  - Drawing of Blue Hill Harbor, Maine, illustration for A Goodly Heritage, by Maitland de Gogorzo. Ink on paper, singed by artist on verso, as well as annotations., undated (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - The Edge of Darkness (New York: W. W. Norton, 1957)
    - Galley proofs, with printer's annotations, 1957 Jun 13 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Galley proofs, with revisions and printer's annotations, 1957 Jul 22 (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - Galley proofs, with Chase's corrections and annotations, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - The Psalms for the Common Reader (New York: W. W. Norton, 1962)
    - Galley proofs, with printer's corrections and annotations, 1961 Dec 13 (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - Galley proofs, with Chase's corrections and annotations, 1961? (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Uncut page proofs, with printer's annotations, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - The White Gate: Adventures in the Imagination of a Child (W. W. Norton, 1954)
    - Galley proofs, with printer's corrections and annotations, 1954 Jun 15 (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Galley proofs, with printer's corrections and annotations, 1954 Jul 19 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Galley proofs, with some printer's annotations. 5 leaves only, 1954 Aug 5 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - Uncut page proofs, with some annotations, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 120)